Guide to the Elihu Yale Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elihu Yale collection
1610-2000
MS 566
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.25
(9 boxes)
A miscellaneous collection of documents, printed or photocopied, by and about Elihu Yale. Included are records of the Agency of Fort St. George (Madras, India), 1679-1692, during the years of Elihu Yale's governorship, biographical and genealogical materials, copies of correspondence (1699-1719) with Catherine and Elihu Nicks and material on Madras, India and Wrexham, Wales. In the few family papers are a copy of the will of Thomas Yale (1619), the "Recipe book" of Lady Bab North, written for Elihu Yale's granddaughter, memorabilia, and photographs of Yale family tombs and portraits.
Yale, Elihu, 1649-1721
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection as a whole is available for research, parts of it may be restricted due to law, university policy or fragility. Any restricted material will be noted as such.
Scope and Contents
The Elihu Yale Collection is a compilation of printed materials and photographs — and a few original documents — concerning Elihu Yale (1649-1721), one of Yale College's early benefactors. The materials cover the dates 1610 (photostat)-1987. Only a small part of the collection could be considered as the papers of Elihu Yale or the Yale family; in almost every case the collection contains only the photostatic copy of a document housed elsewhere (particularly at the Public Record Office in London). The chief exceptions to this are an intriguing eighteenth-century manuscript volume of recipes, prepared for Yale's granddaughter, Lady Barbara North, and one volume of a rare printed catalogue of Yale's estate.
Most of the material about Yale is printed matter, available elsewhere, but there are also notes, typescripts and letters by various people interested in Elihu Yale. Of these, the largest single segment is that collected by Charles Hervey Townshend (1833-1904).
Because of the many sources, and the likelihood that material will be added from time to time, the collection has been arranged topically rather than by author. The more significant items, however, though filed according to topic, are foldered and listed individually. Oversize materials concerning all topics are filed in the folios at the end of the collection.
For further photographs, the reader should consult the "Individuals" section of the Yale Picture Collection. Books about Elihu Yale are catalogued under Ycz. Y2.
Biographical / Historical
In 1671 Elihu Yale was appointed a writer in the East India Company. He was sent to Madras, India in 1672, and became a member of the council and second in command to the governor. In 1687 Yale became president and governor of Fort Saint George. He returned to England in 1699, where he carried on trade in diamonds. In 1718 Yale made a gift to the Collegiate School at New Haven, Connecticut, which, in appreciation, changed its name to Yale College.
India -- Politics and government -- 997-1765; Madras (India); Wrexham (Wales); Yale, Elihu, 1649-1721
- Original accession, Circa 1610-1987; 4.25 linear feet (5 boxes, 1 folio box, 1 folio)
  General note
  FOLIO
  - Letters (Originals in Public Records Office, London. With copy of a letter from Elizabeth L. Saxe to Robin Winks, 1975 Aug 30.)
    - Elihu Yale to Catherine Nicks, 1699-1710, 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Catherine Nicks to Elihu Yale, 1705-1708 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Elihu Yale to Elihu Nicks, 1719 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Henry Tombs to Elihu Yale, 1708 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Edward Harrison to Elihu Yale, 1710 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Receipts, 1698, 1707 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Writings
    - Records of Fort St. George. Diary and Consultation Book, 1677-1681, 1687-1698, 1912-1917 (Box 1, Folder 4-12)
    - Miscellaneous photostats and transcriptions, and related printed matter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family papers
    - Thomas Yale: will (Ms copy. From the Public Episcopal Registry at Chester. With letter from Virgil D. Allen to Donald L. Jacobus.), 1619, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - W.P. Yale: correspondence re: Vaughan Almshouses, 1855-1860 (Box 2, Folder 14a)
    - "Lady Bab North's Receipt Book", Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Writings about Elihu Yale
    Folio
    - General biography
      - Dexter, Franklin B.: notes, transcriptions of documents, correspondence, photograph, 1874-1904, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Francis, Marguerite: "Governor Yale" (mimeograph of radio script, with clipping re: broadcast), 1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Madras (Presidency) Record Office: "Elihu Yale" and "Thomas Wavell" (typescripts), 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Stewart, Nathaniel B.: Yale" (typescript, with mimeograph of another draft, and related correspondence), 1910 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Stokes, Anson Phelps: review of Hiram Bingham's Elihu Yale (typescript), 1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Tibbitts, E.G.: account of the discovery of documents relating to Elihu Yale at Warwick in 1936 (typescript, with carbon of letter to Tibbitts from James T. Babb), 1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Wynkoop, Gerardus H.: "Eliugh Yale (The Wales Yales)" (copy of typescript), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Record of "Eliah" Yale's admission to Merchant Taylor's School (photostat), 1662 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Catalogue of Yale's estate, vol. 3, [1722] (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Miscellaneous documents, printed matter, and memoranda, 1689-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Copies of printed and pictorial matter, and photograph, re: Elihu Yale, Thomas "Diamond" Pitt and John Evans, collected and annotated by Edward J. Hughes, 1716-1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Published articles and miscellaneous printed matter, 1843-1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
    - Genealogy
      - Yale, Elihu (1807-?): letters to Edward C. Herrick, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Miscellaneous notes, printed matter, photographs, 1850-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
    - Wrexham, Wales
      - Gourlay, T.: watercolors of Yale tomb and Wrexham Parish Church, 1905, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Shaw, Robert: drawing of Yale tomb, with related correspondence, 1898, 1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Yale tomb: miscellaneous photographs, sketches, postcards, correspondence, printed matter, 1899-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Wrexham Parish Church (St. Giles): miscellaneous photographs, postcards, correspondence, printed matter, 1828,1901-1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Plas Grono and general: miscellaneous postcards, printed matter, photographs, 1875-1960, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Wales - General
      - Yale, George W.: "The Yales in Wales" and "The Place in Yale" (annotated mimeographs, with letters and enclosures from Gerard E. Jensen), 1951, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1927-1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Bishop Lloyd's House, Chester, England
      - Block, Rudolph Edgar: letter to Samuel J. Record, with photographs, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1956, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Madras, India
      - Bullitt, William C.: letter to Chauncey B. Tinker, enclosing letters from Robert Rostow, Jr., re: tombstones and artifacts, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Ogden, John T.: letters to Alex M. Hammer, with pamphlet on St. Mary's Church, Fort St. George, Madras; "A walk round St. Mary's" (pamphlet), 1958, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Russell, John S., Jr.: "Elihu Yale; His Life and Times in Madras, India" (typescript of Dartmouth thesis), Undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Miscellaneous photographs, postcards, correspondence, printed matter, 1755, 1902-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Yale and Yale College: miscellaneous printed matter, 1836, 1882-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Portraits
      - Correspondence re: purchase of portrait from R. Eden Dickson, 1910-1912 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Vietor, Alexander 0.: "An Elihu Yale Conversation Piece" (photostats of Yale University Library Gazette article, with related photographs, correspondence, and genealogy, re: Chatsworth Group Portrait), 1960-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - Miscellaneous photographs, printed matter, 1910, 1913, 1927, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Artifacts: miscellaneous photographs, printed matter, memorabilia, correspondence, 1916-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Papers of Charles Hervey Townshend
      - "The Plaintiff in Error's Case" (Ms copy of document, with notes), 1717-1721 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - "Pedigree of Yale" (draft and copies of article, with notes and correspondence), 1898, undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - "Yale Wills" (notes, transcriptions, correspondence, printed copies), 1897-1898, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Letters to others (drafts), with notes, 1892-1903, undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Letters from Alfred Neobard Palmer, with photograph, 1898-1903, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Letters from others, with notes by Townshend, 1892-1902 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Notes on Eatons, with transcriptions of documents and clippings, Undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Notes on Lloyds, with transcriptions of epitaphs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - Notes on Tallmadges, with transcriptions of documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Notes on Yales, Undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Notes on various individuals and families with transcriptions of documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Miscellaneous notes and transcriptions, 1892, 1899, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - Miscellaneous items, 1890-1899 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Tricentenary of Elihu Yale as Governor of Fort St. George, Madras, India (1687-1692): stamp covers, printed material, newspaper clippings, and photograph, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Documents
    - Invoice signed by Elihu Yale (original, framed), 1683 (Box 6)
    - Indenture signed by Yale's great-grandfather David Yale (photostat), 1610 (Box 6)
    - Safe passage for ship Borneo Merchant, signed by Yale and others (photostats.), 1685 (Box 6)
      General
      Original is in Accession 2013-M-075; researchers must use this photostatic copy.
    - Printed list of Yale College theses and graduates (photographs. Original in Yale College Triennial Catalogues.), 1718 (Box 6)
    - Evans, Susan A.: "Ancestry": genealogical account of the Evans and Yale families (photostat of Ms), 1915 (Box 6)
  - Memorabilia
    - Rubbing of inscription on silver platter presented by Yale to St. Mary's Church, Fort St. George, Madras, with letter from Shepherd Stevens, 1933 (Box 6)
    - Drawing of Wrexham Parish Church, with related printed matter, 1915 (Box 6)
    - Etching of St. Giles Church, Wrexham, by J. Bruce Barkley, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Sign from exhibition commemorating 300th anniversary of Yale's birth, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Printed matter
    - Yale genealogical charts, 1962, undated (Box 6)
    - Newspaper article on relation of Ferris family to Yale (photostat, with letter from Edward H. Leete), 1867, 1933 (Box 6)
    - Article on Yale portraits, 1913 (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    - Yale tomb, Undated (Box 6)
    - Wrexham Parish Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - David Yale tomb in Madras, Undated (Box 6)
    - Silver platter, Undated (Box 6)
    - Yale portraits, Undated (Box 6)
  - Yale, Elihu (1807-?): genealogical chart, 1850 (Box 7)
  - Photograph of snuff box portrait, Undated (Box 7)
  - Photograph of indenture signed by Elihu Yale as one of four assignees of commission of a bankruptcy award and photograph enlargement of Yale's signature and seal, 1718 July 31 (Box 7)
- Additional materials, Accession 2002-M-040
  Scope and Contents
  This accession consists of research materials relating to Elihu Yale compiled by Professor Bruce Stowe for use by Yale's Tercentennial Committee.
  - Correspondence, 1986-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes, bibliographies, chronology, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Genealogy chart, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional material, Accession 2013-M-075
  - Safe passage for ship Borneo Merchant, signed by Yale and others, 1685 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Due to its physical nature, researchers must use the photostatic copy of this document located in box 6 of the original accession.